all right the time still 30-some I make an attempt to to put something on
the website half an hour ago so the lecture from last Tuesday and today's lecture
must be there okay the rest is available starters I'm going to be collecting what
I had coming okay and I think probably two more on will email those register
some topics from books to read let's see another announcement we're going to post an
early homework but it's nobody need you for another three weeks or so but I
want you to just know what
is coming and just not reading and in the process of the homework we're going
to have recitation tomorrow so should we can introduce you to yesterday we did move
what you have done introducing led me to some programming aspects cocoa from vista graphical
focus because I think the Wake is preparing the homeworks he wants you to start
building little libraries that eventually lead to large-scale problems now if you don't want us
to develop this libraries in homework 1 we're gonna pass the solutions so you can
use from the second part hours but lastly whatever we post does it means the
right thing I mean we are also students and we post whatever so hopefully you
can do better than than us and hopefully there are solutions we post are your
solutions that's why I want you to factor right up and paste okay and what
was the other announcement and so in this process of we will have a recitation
this Friday but as I told me
very station the same ways the lectures are not thorry so if you don't like
to see me you don't have to come you know there are video lectures everything
is online you can watch me from your kitchen basically we're getting a cup of
coffee but there's gondola station at the same time of driving and again net1 Authority
because hold information will be posted
and so the homework the Lexus okay so you will notice when you reveal the
slides from let's do one there are some
topics that are not covered okay now those topics are really some little bit more
examples from the concepts that was
trying to communicate some of them are going to come in this lecture so I
don't have to do them some lady 3d will cover on Friday some we have
to read them on your own okay and but if there is anything essential I
will go back to it okay if I don't cover it means we don't really
need it for the shell code so for
example there is a big case study of publicity graphical model related to the biology
and as you guys know there is
nobody from biology actually I was asked yesterday polygamy I said we have any students
in biology doing this type of
things like not sorry you know so I don't know if I stopped working for
20 minutes in biology and I did clicker on the slide maybe a third of
humans reached biology and that is not gonna be  good right  pointing all the way around okay
we're going to start discussing a limit about conditional independence relations and graphs but the
context of theoretical aspects of this conditional independence relations not the graphs represent this is
sort of an impure much so we will probably go back to it again and
again for the next 23 weeks so we
have a very reduced understanding so - you can take the concepts today the lecture
scrolling up you'd be easy but
you know you don't have from the stir everything ok this is if you have
variables are showing absolutely zero independence relations this is an appreciation of the visionary all
right so look at it carefully all right not x1 x2 given x1 x2 be
given x2 x1 several different positions like that because for example I can start with
x2 and the next one you will
experience x3 given you know x1 and x3 etc etc so in essence you have
very shove those and in some ways are not symmetric right the way that I
write them so same sort of symmetry sphere ok this expansion is very expensive to
do so just nibble on this if we have you say K values for its
variable X and you have both no so this will require a table of the
order of KT power V and
this is the reason really we started probabilistic graphical models because we be asking a
question structures can you actually simplify this conditional distributions accountable for some independence relations other
ways you know looking at this is well explore given x1 depends on x2 and
x3 telling the trend of x2 and x3 the answer is yes we would factorization
that is very efficient so the discount that I did here it does not account
for normalization of each of these probabilities which is really it doesn't remove much of
the cost and so when you want a perfect one you can okay numbers to
describe it k square to describe excellent even x1 take you to describe this and
take the power bill escape to describe now we'll study machine learning right if you
have missed admission like that and if you want to visit in the context in
the self classification problems there's a lot of text you can do but you don't
have to deal with complexity of K to the me and so here's one example
I'm going to making tables for each of this conditional probability distributions but inverse you
replace them with logistic regression ordinates looks like  that
alright so delicious that you see here it's so tight and we're from the field
itself in here it depends on all the
previous axis so I try to fit this distribution of science enjoyed a function with
a rival of somewhat it's doubly times the vector X for a for the previous
ones and then we may have not
seen this but yeah vs. are different there's no no services sigmoid function and the
focus of a label to take the K
component of the argument and there is a nice model for this provision from a
movie of them and you won't have to fix a thing with to describe them
okay now it's not but the question is normally and I have the calculation here
so if anybody has any places from the power I get it it's actually still
taller than they want you to do the odds of those different against yourself so
it comes out of the the the post of this is K times miss Claire
before the possible straight to the power of me you know it's okay to whisper
so it's really I mean depends offensively is but they they significantly reduce from above
course okay however this method is not
very useful because each of this conditional distributions depends on the values of all the
other previous variables so you want to be able to do maths very sort of
business in the college software plus fire so if you want people mixtures and you
want five modules you know account for evidence and things like that you won't be
able to do the algebra using this module okay but again there is more than
this one we have the tables nice fried this had some function alright and in
this case a few this matrix not many once you have it then this could
be an easy problem figure in the context of classification so what I want to
do this in this course we won't do something better some basic  things probability integral syndrome
conditional independence so I have 1 divided by XY and Z can be scalar K
vector so I say that x and y are
conditionally independent given Z 1 FX 2 the y and z is equal to B
FX given C ok so tom is a normal something of Drive make a difference
when it comes to the value of x okay so this is one way to
I'd the traditional dependent of X for y
double Z this important that's why you say conditional because there is an argument either
now cosmas if you think this is a definition let me say the simple algebra
right I can write this more effectively y and z and then P of Y
given Z so those are this I can write
this as P of X given Z P of Y given C so we can
advances in the Commission to life as an alternative way that when this conditional distribution
for price is like knob Direction Y an independent commission along Z okay so sometimes
this will be convenient sometimes this
they are exactly the same thing that's  good
okay dependence relationship also in terms of sets of random variables so we can either
assent affection for environments is developing once that wagon easy when texas independent of Y
given Z for every X in the set X and
everyone in the sidewalk okay and actually this Zia can make it also set so
I maybe that we have been even
more generalized reversals in there now for example we say this set of the very
most is independent that given that set
variable so this basically will follow  this definition here
the repellents we listen to this sort of orthogonality condition but in some probability looks
mr. personality condition may imply something else usually defined in terms of expectations okay but
for us this is the notation we're
going to use muscle independence basically you know we take this definition for example means
of perfection y is given p FX he apply okay I was just looking at
this slide right you can stab it sometimes because you see for example have I'm
using the notation carrying them in a violent way but hopefully we can still get
the message for example you know here I lose capital X and wife on the
bottom was here in little x and y then effectively the same force but you
know traditionally this would be the lot of the volume or this will be the
values that are the vitamin can take but you know we're okay right we're not
gonna see you know sorry you with a little X you know it's gonna tell
you I type this slide at least we have some slides to talk about the
wrong papers you know it's good idea to sort of be careful and consistent because
much than you're consistent okay so this mess intent of this conditional and marginal independence
okay so I am saying here
that this whole time is independent of  the type of the car okay
[Music]
I mean the you know they say the probability of a is higher is you
know I mean they you know would be exactly the opposite effect from the first
example okay so so this is the motion again so we're gonna verse here you
know I'm writing this is a standard are gonna spend actually two or three lectures
discussing about this kindle market or
in the State Park Estate state-space models but this is a Markov chain so we
can imagine you know you have some state
body moves but and you know the values of it Connie so x1 is the
volume of dynomonics - thank you it cetera so the unusually a monomial assumption here
where the model effects of high BP depends only on the value of I'm XT
minus 1 so prepared this expression show expecially we can remember this pretty does this
long expression compared list right with this Markovian model that is very simplified because extra
doesn't depend on XT minus 2 XT minus 3 etc ok so this is this
moment they see various cues the
independence relations in particular but XP is independent X 2 minus 1 is in the
parent of all the various values XT
minus 2 X 1 on this course or something if I highlighted from lecture 1
which is the parent of the node right so in this case if we look
at no business to parents okay and so here's a fundamental
fairness conditionally previous relations for this directed graph and so what it says x-ray is
independent from the main the segments of a negative spiral so this is out there
Tamara trenched to emphasize the depositor given this will highlight in that movie alright so
the parlance it stays that the value of
V is independent through the name of the sender so photographer at the political order
the wrong descendants will have numbers but they are basically everything about the values of
the parents basically in the order okay these are the non descendants right so point
on the values of the parents
excuse you the fella from the non-descendants eye or anything like that right so view
at this point I just want you to visualize as to what this means because
we love I think we should
highlight that which is not very difficult but once you have this the composition for
probability defined on this graph you move rains pushing too hard okay so we will
able to take advantage of this relation so and no Pascal will ensure that only
distillation of the fertilizer in this
graph satisfies this relation and around this dilution on the graph this relation is also
satisfied you know I mean you
can see sorry  alright so both ways this will be okay
that the capitalization of the joint of immunity on the restive graph is written as
the product over all the nodes of the
graph of the conditional probabilities of X I excite the volume of you know the
I given the violence apart this is an
amazing between position if you think about it right so you know in this case
the conditional probability corresponding to its no and this function is the condition of the
way the effects are given its forests so mr. Bastian that factorization with this graph
the personal missile dependent relation that we introduced which is certified ethical justification for deewana
and discuss its Lewis okay so I
will have exactly tricentennial examples and some a little bit more complicated but I'll ask
you to know mrs. Blaine and
electric artworks and washing us if we  can prove it
[Music]
Rises and this factors here these functions are the condition for committees of X i
given sparks when we have this complicated factorization from the product rule well we only
have the parents we have taught the settlers and the co parents and the novice
and everything else is coming here but because of this independent relationship the the only
partition here this X i given the parents of
so I'm actually so sure what I'm doing I am taking a directed graph with
my body moves the first equation writes the the product rule so no independence assumptions
I am love assuming nothing and then I am applying sort of this equation right
I'm applying this equation that says that business innovation is factorized this way and another
thing at this the predominate affects one because it's one has no parents all right
the prevent effects still given x1 that's the only part I could still get enough
only x1 x4 given 2 and 3 and X 5 given 3 so remember you
can see the appearance relations that
effectively whether says the probability is equal to naught which means the level x3 expires
in the penitent water I mean
looking at this 2 equation there never expiry x5 is independent off that's 124 right
there it's here given x2 x3 x4 is
independent of X 1 given X 1 X 3 in terms of X 2 etc
you may say I know but
how do I know this independence relation  well we will spend a lecture or two and  we will
cases
it's okay you know this if let's say is the number of parents to the
power left to describe this times times
in principle actually somebody can say take the power a plus one
you sit up but you know it's like if you're comfortable a normalization and everything
so that's approximately of the order wine is take aid to affect
reverse right these are going to take a values and we're taking K values all  right so okay less rough
yes NZ's enemy remembrances lesser dismissed mara independence relations okay and this is not very
interesting so this is something very just the Ascension this you can appreciate the necessary
I'm showing that this function is a  probability right because you say 116  points along that mystical did you okay
the distributions okay next one to experience equal to one which is nice so obviously
it's individual on normalizing expect that this will be the case and apparently this the
composition here you can show that the national experience is actually it comes home service
functions is really the conditional distribution which is what I tell you you need to
remember okay this functions are very more general and they don't even have to be
preferable if this but right now from directed graphs this is the case and I
say the proof and it works on extremely busy slide all right that's why I
want you to type your homework because this rule was the lazy person typing the
slide my secretary the novelist which imaginary person alright so it was me okay because
I can't imagine asking anybody that I've destroyed so it was this I want you
to to need some type and by typing fails so
that because you will need to do this for specific distribution your homework to do
things like that so the first part
of the theorem was methods and responses  individually
[Music]
the secrets wirelessly was one of the signals along okay sort of calculation that is
going to make the relations of
the article of all those extremely efficient okay define in terms of the notes and
the values of the parents minds within the operations rather in this case the marginalization
is a local operation right and this allows us to to  see immediately the distance
it's his Michigan the normalized properly okay okay mr. as I say those any functions
like that take the permanent zone distribution well I'm going to show you know that
this and some of the various I write lists as the joint effects k plus
1 and the quality k plus 1 divided by the powers of k plus 1
and then I I calculate the numerator
denominator using the appropriate  marginalization of the composition of  the joint of a new distribution
expansion sure whatever done
okay okay okay so this is the okay mr. Lucius okay because that's positive wearing
dark shirt and whatever else on
the proctors so let's take this one and  the partnership give you some k plus and
and because I have to forensic aware that if L doesn't create the pilots of
k plus 1 is inside before camp yesterday right so I don't have to worry
about the parent and mr. McCann needed to learn outside the estimation because I don't
samel XK plus one or departments and you
notice from here to there I have to sound and the professionals from 1 to
K except the parts of campus where  elements will be possible  explain right there without a freshwater
because this is something extremely important right because I'm doing I'm pushing the summations inside
I have a context that the potentials are okay according to my induction argument they're
really the conditional distributions and then I have this summation of the other factors that
have no clear benefit so if you do this and we move this on the
local what you have to summon XK plus 1 because there's no X 2 plus
1 so this whole transformation constants numerator denominator D summation constants and this factorization by
definition is 1 because this functions are normalized so what I get is this conditional
distribution is equal to my factor FK plus 1 so as you
compose in revenue distribution in terms of conditionals the proof is not shortened to contagious
is like traffic AIDS ok actually most books the parties consider a logician there's no
proof okay inaudible any questions on this thing's right if another story our interest is
really the decomposition in terms of these local conscious that their conditional the values of
exodus 12 given its parents the resumption topology will here the destructor fundamental to the
type of things we do this with directed graph and the part that we have
it illogical or derivative is decelerations and insulation don't imagine that they have to sound
x1 an actual appears in all of these  functions
myself but the tractor fixed islands only on the bottom here exclusively there right so
obviously in this problems you can start some you provide to the left all right
and if examples as you see this so
that's important and then you'll notice you have some operations to put rods and notes
where we sum up although the rest
of the body most this is so focused on the operation we we have to
do with a glass with left of model stressing the context of why not kids
like the different there is a problem to the complex all right I'm I always
like the opposite of the normal
case right I remember you know I said maybe this joke some time ago I
was trying to give a whole action on some topic and some people ask me
can you start to give an example and I have not been introduced what the
topic was okay you know she'll never leave my case alive to give you the
period when the examples come later on he do the examples on your own so
yes sort of the people in one day so extra depends on X 1 X
2 X 2 etc so you can see I say okay
of the write this as a product of the functions but intellectual inspires this is
nothing then experian the partner physics wonder next year and the pharmacist our experience it's
for the next three so the other ones you can show you at least the
service functions they are nothing else or the the function of P of X clinics
still is when the condition of x3 given x2 and I think mr. composition right
and I I you know the country first I have to calculate the joint if
X to X T divided by T FX still so then the other thing I
have to some obviously to marginalize
it's all X 1 X 2 X 4 or X 1 and X 4 and
you can see some of the things we'll
organization can see long distance inside the trial and these parenthesis and visible practice comes
too long to learn good idea to is f 3 or X 3 and X
3 just is like a turbulent completed version of the theorem okay the best possible
functions right and this conscience turn out to be pro communities is only for directed
graphs we said anything for undirected graphs the case to be very well general management
of sanity can position at least in the context of this Markov chain about adoption
being a bit more powerful so this is an example from one of the textbook
similar in machine learning so one of the notes is the glass is left one
of the knowledge is the support which can be on the left the other one
is a know that is raining
which can be on earth and everyone is that it's cloudy I am a strong
basically the dependencies look like the hot all right and let's follow the fuel that
I described the junket ability of drama straight away the grass right is basically returnest
same time first even see we're forgiven see what not really given us an hour
and everything you can see by comparing this with examining the composition using the product
community to share is implies basically fundamental national independence relations right and as a measure
of the elections okay right that
you can this you can expect this independence relations all right and then from this
you can say oh that's why
the composition I mean in Pascal the new activist problem and you have this graph
like that smells you already have a
negative in the graphics independence relations so this decomposition is automatic you don't have to
clear anything right so we are going to define this distribution so effectively the trial
value well because of an organization to define this is from his first loudest row
so if I do he wanted
as long as the other one is one line is nervously than one value let's
say this is the probability of the specular the hell are they so I am
writing is probability well the cloud is a false argument or a tool to describe
this well actually I have no
money from this I have to fill this I have different Lee's and if I
take this little mini be how isn't it okay we come from the normalization because
for a lot of skilled problem it doesn't make a sense to say - wah
- wah yeah we can subtract - fish - a problem with million borrowers we
will make a difference okay so no bother so I spent the card for this
problem is the times to the
carry case the number of points below and this environment variables that's why you see
it through there actually I don't know why I different from before before using were
using K from the number of values that are available can take here I just
a for another opponent the game you guys are adult and vaccinated so you can
figure out in which life what the context is right so so I don't have
to go back and change the story that's already there and I was sure that
everybody responds what this equation makes or let's the the correlation rate across today from
directly ghost makes a little sense
there was nothing else okay all right
so this 11 example I think I'm gonna I may have to give this because there's
unpleasant dependence relations from this example as applications in the slides so this is prevalence
of you know to come you know sometime in the near part of a future
so there are such variables and best on with the discussion of in the composition
this is what I have right x1 x2 given x1 x3 given X 1 X
5 etc X tix given X 2 X 5
protected right and and you say in this example a nice graphical representation of the
table society to this conditional distribution is corresponding to each tsunami so x1 it's a
long experience given x1 so it's a baby like this exports given x2 table like
this exist given two values okay it's a table like that and like that I
have to actually program I'm assuming and I'm saying this that show the kid and
take note and destroy that we assign you some homework problems when we don't do
the question all right you have something only  computer program to do this for you
don't eat this don't eat this already did this Antoni gaudí
okay guys there's a time for them how's that possible I don't have the power
you know why not a very good machine ever left of their other thing you
guys left me because you'll never never go almost papers right that's the 30 minutes
all right let's see necessarily put so I'm going  to my past
and okay so which of the sexist is coming all right so then this is
our independent of each other and that's the concept of the latest Paris fire okay
so so it's my NRI all right this are independent if I didn't know why
they're nervous values of X 1 and X 4 whatever I get they depend on
each other this is sort of a song another problem will reduce you know in
in sort of mixed models but many other settings as well  okay
two things - one and two long is this Belgium to mislead Gaussian so if
I wrote a little bit of white for it sex the this exercising defendant and
so effectively you know this is the problem engine roaring tons of the divinity of
the world X given Y and the lamented
world X living who soldier sex is given Y can be factorized over the data
right because of this assumption that the X is having a fairly given Y ok
so so this is something very important laughter moment of birth under the name of
naive Bayes classifier i mean i
satisfy a fear you know i know this but additionally basically has been this is
that that's fine to say become from now
someone and thousand through so that's what the name plus pi or take this complexed
and say the sections are linearly independent given y and you notice on this paragraph
if you see on the birthday all right I started fatal dependencies between the exes
okay so this is the display the
printed my Vegas was fired okay to come up with your own little algorithms and
this if you search in the literature you
will find very particular algorithm it's for leveling this demented name they discussed fire okay
yes well I just know if you remember that name basements that these types of
sex running right and independent so you have a nice proposition that looks like this
okay and constants with dependencies between the extras and because the balance is still maintained
some pay structure that you can do is the difference but the  custom what you see on the top okay
it's prevalent conditional independence relations National Defense relations so these actions right so this is
all right this is the length of appearances this is referred directly best luck sir
okay and the party dependencies we have this one we introduced the Vegas more longer
in about two legs from now so you can
work from something from collective one  connected personal between the first
okay there is nothing new there
but I am descendants even the parents then the descendants even the parents  and
accept the fact the fundamental property of directed graphs the different position from the parable
sprouts to convince your sensitive actually again the fulfilled never step two is this marginalization
that we did in two examples before and then you can treat  this decomposition is correct
[Music]
one extreme
experts in the time of x1 x2 and there's not wrong exterior to this efficient
right
- okay listen tada your life is perfect when it's the expected by P of
X 1 is 50 ok by you
alpha plus X 1 X 2 X 3 X 4 is that what happens to
X 5 and X 6 fear of insulin
what happened to X 5 minus X 6 well I mean the question of attack
the black is words you know when you somewhere X 5 and X 6 this
is 0.1 of this equal to 1 so they disappear you see that when you
analyze to the joint the next 5 minutes because this how conditional distinguishes the summation
is giving the advantage okay so so this
is the joint of X 1 X 2 X 3 X 4 and then if
you wanted to join the pitch 1 X 2 X
3 we have to something that's clear but when someone experimenting disappearing because summation of
expelling everyone all right yeah well this consus without this concept evolved already but you
get this perfect score given X 2 okay so this is kinda filled this independence
relation but I wrestle to remember the ideas that Assad isn't behind all of this
and say all there is an independence relations but to heaven all the groups of
this graph and he says this graph implies none of this independence relations so whatever
distribution that population the graph has been tamarkan satisfy of this relationship okay a stupid
idea so we're not going to
do the algebra but we lived  that vision server browser arguments  implants University what is relationship
and here is an over in the Paris relation X 1 given X 6 is
the head of X 3 X 3 this is like in the in this case
of disease that say cancer and why is
somehow kind of a disease you know some of molecule blood or other things so
why is the disease right but the memory access many diseases and you have something
that can be derived from any
diseases so you can see this as a little from X to Y so exist
another thing the - you can see this is awareness problem that if you have
an alternate and let's say a blood test you ask the members area and so
this graph that you see in
spitzer discuss you know this isn't about the narrative rondelle the joint affection Y as
the probable effects knives the probability of Y given X so reliable addressed you know
this you know the parent effects may be will  define it by
right right okay
[Music]
delicious from X to Y but that doesn't allow you can be any friends res
or something for y and say what desserts  okay
they delivered the next two slides we will discuss and rain
okay right okay so this is the right
[Music]
dress is wet but let me let you know whether Dre
this has already explained that the grass is wet okay we will formally serve this
with a derivation okay but in essence if this  example all right
no problems maybe today
with little names let's say you have two points the students are doing the kind
of it thank you go gents you know come
to get doesn't depend on anything so they're putting the feather corns let's say this
and this right so let's Alchemist is right this is zero okay so this has
exploratory they so right so this is Center for the experiment a  phenomenal
I was reporting this in the slides you know losing the game in the factorization
which we miss you can actually compute an audience and do the algebra nothing Ranger
so this is the factorization we started so you can actually prove all the questions
that you saw in the previous slides
my ass Douglas relation so let me just say what's going easier so remember we
sent that you know X of the royal
descendants okay so basically the board is independent of anything else okay the SAT score
or what rate is clearing out
that cetera  question on the doctor okay it says
parasocial was given them the difficulty of an exam all right it's also kind of
hell okay that's not what I wrote it
however informational says about its descendants
well so long I just want the sentence against not breathing with an equation any
information about the descendants contains beliefs about this invention reasoning process so another race if
you know what happened was still there it has got there okay it changes the
picture okay even who says the difficulty on the intelligence of the Skinner right if
the evidence is the difficulty of in Excel and even peasants sugar still smells but
the official from below the most immortality do the fixer okay so we will see
this sort of problem when we discuss  independence relationships and and  evidence okay
[Music]
okay
and this would be the growth and the logo is this image on just the
mission we have sent up over all the she's invaluable success okay so then this
have the visceral volume is the Sabbath
even vartanus and this is sort of the main cost that allows you develop native
environments now the only thing I was
gonna say is a little socially desirable but Sir I was seven gardeners there was
the number of mobile growth so
we can think of a gradual and that way the death of our decisions coming
so the killer virus can be maybe indicator punch values that tells you what it's
beautiful collect - what Gaussian envelopes are they too late or what you know okay
so life is the composition is right that this hidden garden was the morning with
a number of the additional volume which in the graph  you can keep the prosperous
service parameters theta are independent but independent of the data you collect in the problem
okay sure and in real problems here in the formation of the rebels will go
to be able to achieve is a testament to this  data parameters theta but this bottom of
missions to carefully account for the factors and somehow instance you have to do predictions
by information of the students to know is nobody here in a few weeks from
now but because not wait a
minute and the very natural self directly linked to my website at least the previous
one and this nice already aware and I will see here on next  Tuesday suppose