throughout this part we supposed to start obviously you realize the lectures are videotaped that's
why I have to start exactly 1213 I suppose I have your permission with the
tape here we are not actually in the video but if you say anything also
you don't have to worry because
it's not going to pick you up very micro points which made but the lectures
are going to be videotaped and posted on the  website of the course and also on what's  the system
but you know we put the lectures from YouTube so you can download them directly
from the next notes the course
website it's an under construction which means it's only the link is there the rest
is going to be up when I managed to
get some sleep of 12 hours deadlock okay so maybe tomorrow or something you know
certainly before the next lecture I hope to have this thing up with today's lecture
and video as well let's see the glass is Tuesdays and Thursdays 12:32 unqualified I
know there has been lots of changes from the timing it's really not something I
control when you use the lecture room like 126 the Bartolo that has videotaping you
know everybody wants this room so it's very difficult to watch that yes everything is
on yeah thank you thanks for stopping by so this room is on high demand
so we were in then we were out in and out so we are in
as of today the Baku next
rescue station first place and maybe not every Friday but once a while we're going
to have recitations to get we've
helped with a homework and in addition when there are missing lecture I'm going to
use cry this to cover up for that so
let's see what else that's my email address whatever information you need I want to
try to provide it on the course
website okay there's a lots of there you know regarding the course objectives this is
not an application course right that don't usually teach application of courses so Vista course
on the fundamentals of community graphical modules and I remember someone's had asked me in
the past you know what's probabilistic graphical models thinking must be something graphical you know
probably the graphical models is a
constant yet is a way to work with many random variables and if you think
this many of the valuable some somehow interconnected because they are correlated there is a
graph and then maybe we can do some graph theoretic approaches to doing transpose but
don't expect to have a problem where there is a graph and then you say
oh do something with this graph the graph is there all right so you have
to think of something being represented as a graph and I think it comes tense
that's the most difficult part of of the of the cost being able to actually
visualize on how what is a good
model to represent the relations between many other body okay so I'm going to try
to give you all the fundamentals to do
inference in graphs and when I talk about the interest rate refer to Bayesian inference
I'm going to discuss both directed and undirected graphs maybe people in social science do
psychology they like directed graph people in science and engineering the like undirected graphs but
we've received some how we can connect the different types of graphs we learned one
all the types quite easily obviously you
know I'm going to give you examples here and there represent the potential of using
graphical models from standard machine learning problems the computer vision to doing scientific computing two
certifications of natural language processing computational biology I don't  believe we have anybody from biology the  audience do we  okay
obviously nobody does anything related to the type of things so we don't have anything
any contributions from students this year right well the course is appropriate basically for students
in math statistics and computer science for students in engineering that have good mathematical skills
but very relevant and students in all areas of time this including cognitive sciences biology
if it's called chemical etc some of this course is to not universally so popular
I'd noticed for example you go to
Stanford the cost is more than click on the students attending again because there is
interest from every direction ok here
you have the selective ones are not the same we have the carrots to come
and attend these lectures to Delhi and I hope to see you on with the
next lecture on Thursday as well okay and I hope to see you the day
after I give the first homework because usually that's when the class population goes down
by 50% okay now B this is not that caused us to get four credits
I am assuming you only reason you're here is because you want to learn the
topic and integrated with your research and I'm going to help you in doing that
but if you just need four
credits this is on the right course for you okay I want to you know
this is a very hot important area in many ways and I'm going to educate
you but to be able to learn this you need to have and interest from
the top if you don't this is not the place to be now the cost
you know it's going to be
one of the core courses from the new center for informatics and computational science is
basically the second in sequence from a course to PI I taught on Bayesian statistics
in the fall if you don't really need the previous course and if you need
something well I mean when I say you don't need it you need everything right
the more you know the better but I cannot expect you that you know what
was covered to the previous course so when there are some fundamental concepts that we
need to bring in I will either cover them in this course where I will
give you know it's basically to read about them I think and it is possible
that I'm gonna go back to you some of the topics covered in the poll
anyways but try to address them in a graph theoretic wonder okay so new algorithmic
problems we cover for example related to data stimulation so you need to know probability
theory you don't know anything about probabilities period will disappoint you you need to know
the fundamentals at least Vegas rules and the lights about Bayesian inference and if we
have taken even an introductory cost to must in learning may be useful okay machine
learning for me means computational statistics so whatever we need I will bring it back
for your convenience but it is going to
be helpful if you have a book in your desk but you can look for
information okay and I'm going to give you lots of readings that you can go
through this semester and also after the course is over you need to know programming
because we will make an effort every
homework didn't have a computational problem and we're going to try to do this even
on the first homework these are the first home mortgage deduction calculations but what going
sort of to try to give you a computer assignment simply because we you know
we want to precise this because that these computers is not to do ten calculations
there's too much you know computation
and ten calculations were not tempted to  do any serious problems okay all right
like in the fall semester of relying on the help from others around the court
so dr. Rubik Chakraborty this neck you
know the over there with his mark is going is volunteering to help with some
of the vegetation preparing some of the
homework solutions and also doing some of the grading and so he's gone around the
resistance and maybe once if I give
a lecture or two when I'm out of town so the homework is going to
be submitted electronically to this email address I'm going to provide more information on the
website in the cover that you need to
submit the homework this address may change actually by tomorrow that's why I said this
email address this is a Google
email account but you may have made  design one just for this class okay
I notice some of you look worn oh yes you know we like typed homework
because it is for me especially computational silence and writing by 10:00 there's no way
we can figure out what you're
writing there if you write if you type something nice to me it is very
easy to know what is going on okay so indeed with preferred type homework but
some of your lazy and I'm referring
to my students my own students so for those who are lazy you can stop
the you can stick on your homework and stormy if there's a PDF attachment okay
if you do this thing's might can't ask me you will identify 90% of the
mistakes in your homework just by typing it slowly and looking at it say oh
it doesn't look good and it doesn't look good mint is wrong okay but if
you tied by hand it never looks good so you never have lost is it
right because most of the time is
wrong okay so we learnt that convert not to mention you know what if you
type this nice 3 tomorrow you go for a job interview and you say yeah
I took this course and here is what I did and that counts a lot
ok because this is not intro to happy hour type of port let's see the
information on how you have to uch your homeworks and how to name
touch your homeworks and how to name your submission again sir I will give that
information of the website MOOCs I'm gonna start actually in different orders from what is
given here the this book by Michael Jordan and introductions published graphical models is actually
what is used in most universities for breeding and it's actually turtlecom you know everybody's
taste in preparation reprint this book has been in preparation for 25 years which means
professor jonathan has given up basically because things are changing so rapidly it's like what's
the point of finishing this book now okay and so versus actually the easiest and
the most insightful reading that you can have and for those who register in the
course I am going to send you a PDF so I shouldn't be saying this
on faith somehow you've been going to library find it okay all right the let's
see if you really want to do research in this area a heavy book that
you need to have in your desk is the textbook by Colin is written is
more than a thousand pages maybe 1,200 pages has a lot of information some we
will cover it in this course in detail some all the details you don't need
them but toughen the vistas the state of the art both in theory and algorithms
so business you know recommended book basically or you know to have the the textbook
that we usually fit last fall by Kevin Rushdie has you know it's like an
encyclopedia of machine learning it's not really a readable text book but it has lots
of new algorithm still much more modern Abroad's and it has a structural also that
goes with all the examples in the
book which I recommend it right and it is actually less probabilistic than for example
Jordan's reprint okay it used likes to use point estimates for fast inference for most
of the algorithms but you know there are I don't know six seven chapters are
thinking for published graphical models and we will cover at least the essential parts of
those this of just one chapter
on probabilistic graphical models that is actually an ideal read if you want to know
everything about this court before we even start to get a good stance let's say
this week is to read what's after is
it a a so if you're in separate even just without the details alright just
going through it it would serve you
extremely well because it has everything not loops or anything like that but has the
lots of insights as to what
probabilistic graphical models are and how to go about okay so certainly this would be
a good start point and also if he has the cube has many other things
that utilized the machinery of probabilistic graphical models that we will also use in this
course 16 readable most probably the most readable book on machine learning in the market
and even watched about 20 years tall you will find it I pressed when I
read it every other day I
find something new there okay and so I obviously I recommend all of this book
okay grading so we're going to have six
homework the homework will be 60% of the grades and it be a project 40%
for some maybe that's too much you know but if you think about it no
exams no meters no finals nothing okay so this is a gradual course we don't
operate the classical way but the expectations are higher than giving an example you write
something wrong page that say congratulations we pass the course right so the project it
the program we have to change the leave it from those who took the course
in in the poll because I was very disappointed with the attitude of many students
here when it comes to the course to the project I get freedom to everybody
to define their own project relevant to the course and I can tell you there
were at least seven students who came up with a new definition of the project
about three days before the presentation I mean asked not normal just ridiculous okay so
so I don't know exactly how
we're going to do it but I'm gonna think in the next two or three
weeks but the possibility would be to actually literally five you ten twenty projects and
save it to Z and here are the
references become whatever you like and do one of those and you cannot say right
well we may do it as last fall but
with strict guidelines that you changed project means you get zero breaking your project we
cannot allow basically a week before
the representation solidifying what the project is and I'm not talking about the trying a
little bit I'm talking about going from A to Z okay not to mention going
from A to Z and SIF having no
relation to the course at all right so that's number I take so certainly I
want with the project to give you an opportunity to do something that is relevant
to your research right so that
not only you benefit because you learn the material of the course for those strong
you benefit because the course in
fact you're already served and that's very important okay so now because of so the
the project is going to require a
report which is not limited to six pages a written presentation like PowerPoint of Beamer
and another presentation and because we have two dates in the fall with scheduling with
our presentations and videotaping them have not seen any of the videos yet by the
way of artists presentations yet because they have not been provided to me but have
what we're going to do to avoid all that the next weekend we're going to
take maybe the last three or four lectures of the course and we're going to
have the presentations in class so you're going to be on this real video and
not issue because the videos are automatic okay so we don't have to worry about
story there's nothing available in May
sorry in June this building is closed in July is open for something else and
that we're gonna do it in class even if that takes lecture so be prepared
the that the project would be you wave before the end of the semester the
wave means you know three lectures of this before the end of the semester so
we're gonna have to move on the projects quite strong okay the services are very
preliminary so some of these topics we may cover them in lots of details but
some not we're going to discuss as I mentioned directive of the undirected graph this
should be of interest to everybody but
mainly you know in social and in social sciences natural language modeling things I thought
market models are basically essential for people to work in scientific applications we're going to
do it lots of 12 hours for data
simulation problems starting with basically a little relating everything that you may already know from
other courses or not some of these topics we cover them and in the fall
so ideas for example of doing dynamical systems with particle methods now we will see
how to develop the same identical algorithms but with a graph theoretic approach so for
example you can think of doing
Kalman filtering and generalization always with no effort using algorithms on graphs nothing new but
the risk of slipping would grass you babel action to develop your own Oliver effect
you want to that this extension of standard methodologies  that have been around for thirty years
we're gonna spend maybe more than two lectures may be anything from five to ten
lectures to discuss inference in graphs and this concept of exacting first of course is
you know it's not always possible so we are gonna start with this and then
we will so we will cover as part of exactly current idea so far the
new propagation destruction pre algorithm elimination and the light will discuss about approximate inference using
generalizations of means you know means till the type of algorithms so this is an
important area and it actually an earlier that literally goes coefficient with graph theoretic algorithms
so this will be an essential
part of the cost and if we have time I think maybe we spend two
three lectures to discussed on how do you learn the structure of a graph so
if somebody for hours view realizations for a few hundred of variables and you want
to figure out how they are correlated how do we do this how do you
come up with learning destruction of a graph and of course we've realized the this
is a very difficult open problem right so this is actually the fantastic area to
do a PhD not one piece P you can work for 100 feet this because
I don't believe this problem can be scaled many of the variables alright but it's
an important topic that is to be
discussed so the lectures will give in the tape I think we think an hour
two of the lectures are available on Sakai when the website is up if not
today tomorrow we will post these videotapes the on YouTube so will be that youtube
link where the lecture PDFs will be posted I hesitate actually have to think about
this if I want to post the lectures like
we did in the fall so that you have them in front of you during
the lectures because I was observing certain individuals in this room but they are still
clear okay during my lectures basically doing nothing else but just looking on that computer
that's not the way to go I mean
why have you you know I mean they are looking at bookkeeping you can look
at form right since the business will be available this you need to come to
them I mean make me spill good of course if you come and I appreciate
but I think the idea is to be able to benefit even partially by listening
in person to these lectures okay but for sure the lectures will be positive if
not before immediately after you know you know in the afternoon of the same day
there will be a lots of references of papers and books and things I got
that I will link to the lectures so consider those as very useful readings and
also there will be a lot of chalkboard links that you can use this well
why would I forgot this because we're video tape I want to encourage questions but
I'm gonna have to repeat your questions otherwise nobody Houston anything okay so let me
stop there any questions about the structure of it all really there's no structure I
mean we do anything we want to we can change our mind tomorrow all right
we are interest money to learn and not
to go from A to B to C because I there's no such a thing
okay so and feel free to
take advantage drop any questions
of course the question I have to ask is how many of you will love
stick with us on Thursday alright and I hope everybody alright bring the cousins -
okay we need all the support we can get
I mean one of my students is teaching now at Purdue similar course as the
one without clearing in the fall more or less things are a little more basic
but she told me she has more than 60 they had to limit the cluster
talents was fixed it because they were students from every quarter interested but you know
here we're a small population so we
don't have the Nutri of 60 20 is actually a great number for example for
okay but you guys need to not to give up
when I give homework okay if you do give  up I'm sorry for you all right so no  questions
any questions just to entertain the thing no but the way whichever I know who
have at least and students that will
be listening to be stopped from various places overseas okay I have been surprised the
receiving names of students from certain universities in China but they even do the homework
and they submit me corrections to the homework okay so and corrections to the software
of the homework the case though
and I have seen the impact some of this lectures have had on various health
so it served quite rewarding okay so we're going to start with sort of some
elementary introduction to control in a geographical borders discussing some terminology maybe one or two
basic examples I am NOT gonna do any
mathematics linear questions or anything like that but so if you see saying things that
really require a lot of explanations keep in mind and when I come back to
those topics and discuss them in detail as we go along right so this is
just to give you a flavor of what a probabilistic graphical model is and what
the type of promise were interested by the way in addition to the video lectures
if from our course if you served with the constant form you say probabilistic graphical
models you will find notes from many short court system here have heroes living divani
and Christmas of have a series of lectures on probabilistic graphical with videos and PDFs
but you know you can find online the Stanford courses and many other universities the
courses from Cornell etc so you can sort of if you have questions with a
certain topic if you turn you'll be able to find a lot of resources I
think the good thing is this area of machine learning it's an area of a
very open society that likes things out there to be open okay we don't hide
anything everybody can actually benefit and we like it that way
so we're really probabilistic graphical models just to model the relations between many random variables
okay so now effectively would be a way to produce the joint probability of this
body most so X here is a vector so the
probabilistic graphical models will give us sort of file an efficient way to model this
distribution fire fact and something that we would need to be able to take advantage
when we work with grouches we're going to be able to account for the independent
relations between these variables by somehow
dropping some links from the graph as we wish it softly all right so I
have these two variables and they're not connected darkus an implication probabilistically speaking so the
idea here would be that the joint probability distribution when it is factorized according to
a graph or a graph is not right the model in the police relations you
know inside this probability distribution if we do that we will be able to take
advantage of inference algorithms but still very nicely in graphs all right and in some
of the solvent you used completely graph theoretic sort of argument and so they are
very convenient now if somebody if
you if I give you let's say 50 variables and you learn the joint probability
distribution and somehow you can factorize in some nice way the main interest will be
to do inference which means if I knowledge say this stand variables what's the probability
of very many variables all right and so we're going to have to do somehow
develop some algorithms that will allow us to compute marginal and conditional distributions out of
this joint distribution the Adisa Teno the joint we should be able to do lots
of things cheaply and in particular
that will be the case for graphs now when you have a joint distribution like
that you will always have lots of
unknown parameters to define the joint distribution so one of the tasks in probabilistic graphical
model is to figure out what those parameters are given realizations of some random variables
okay so we would see examples
of that
let's go so probably a feminist is basically for military plus graph theory okay we
obviously we won't drop it because
we're graph speak we can visualize the independence relation between the many of the variables
and once we do that we
can motivate the lots of new algorithms I mean the posture can tell you when
I was interested in solving some weird multi scale problems I've as long as visualizing
of how this may look like
and everybody thought that was an idiot because somehow they couldn't see how probabilistic graphical
model can be relevant but if it is here then you should be able to
put it in a computer program okay so visualizing the structure of a probability model
of thing is essential to get nice algorithms all right so we're going to develop
algorithms that they take advantage of this graph structure so we're going to be able
to do inference learning and all of these things affected in the graphs and the
ideas for example of these masters
passing algorithms will be something  that you cannot do without a graph  theoretic approach
so the benefit you get in sizing for the model you look actually graphically and
you can say lots of things as to how the
around the variables correlate to each other you can develop many new algorithms by playing
with the structure of the graph and most of the inference we will do in
this course can scale nicely simply because of this independence relations but implied by by
the gun action and actually I can tell
you that's quite all you don't need to know anything as a background all the
calculations always in machine learning there are nothing else but applications of the solid product
rules of probability and we will see this something on Thursday when we develop simple
things on graphs so realist you
know the definitions of probabilities and what the stomach for the fruits are then you
are ready best bid to do lots
of nice things
but I told you that don't be scared I power lots of concepts because we
will develop all of this in separate lectures so I'm just throwing this as an
introduction so the dart is going to
encode the whatever independence assumptions exist for my many random variables all right and basically
we'll be able to factorize the probability distribution on the graph or given a graph
we will know what type of
factorization the graph complies for the probability distributions that we define the idea is that
somehow this factorization of the joint probability distribution of the graph would be with local
functions that are defined on the
notes of the graph so these local functions will be different things for directed graph
which we also called the Bayesian networks and will be different for undirected graphs that
also we call them a mark of network okay but the idea is somehow a
joint distribution between many of our variables can be written as a product of local
functions and this is great right but it's not so physically what you very did
because if for example you think spatially many of the variables the variables here don't
depend on the volume is their right
correlation sort of local extent so somehow if you can arrange these things to the
graph you have a similar nature
you will be able to do lots of work that is local and from these
local functions you'll be able to say build this this joint distribution of the menu
of the volumes by the way when
I said some wearables of here and there this is in the special context or
in the time context but the goth can be a very abstract entity they have
nothing to do with space of time okay so don't you know again depending on
the type of things you're interested you can envision different scenarios so Bayesian networks are
probabilistic graphical models that are defined on directed graphs and I'm gonna show you an
example shortly and this Markov random pills this Markov networks are basically probabilistic graphical models
for undirected graphs three so these are the main two types right and you can
have some graphs that have some directed component some undirected components and also you can
pose this in sort of some
unified way using what's called photographs and we will discuss verse as well so actually
you know three lectures there's no point of discussion one type or another we will
unify development for all of this at the same time okay the nodes in the
graph we represent are the variables and this is very important the lack of transition
the graph will imply conditional independence assumptions in other ways if I have nodes representing
random variables and I have to take ten variables and I connected smart evil with
every other body world then there's no point of doing graphs because that problem complexity
will never allow you to go
anyway it's somehow some edges are missing that implies to military somebody who don't depend
on all the volume which the lots
what we need to think about so the idea is we are interested in graphs
that they are not fully connected right they are fully connected one of gaining anything
by learning this course right the idea
is not everything depends on everything and we need to learn about part of the
structure problem that we discussed the
second part of the course but again the lack of threads is what represents conditional
independence assumptions and we spend two or three lectures to discuss that and I will
give you a number of formal projects to work on all right so something just
let's go from right in there this is a directed graph I'm gonna give you
the terminology in of the you know in follow up slide but just to get
things going basically here you can use common sense interpretation for now you know so
all of this are other variables we have a b c d e are on
two variables can be continuous or discrete doesn't really matter and the idea here of
the service means that C depends
today and B it depends on C and D right and so this implies this
direction of the arrow the causal relationship alright so big doesn't depend on me it
depends from D that's what I know from
here okay the rest you will need to derive from the factorization employed by this
directive model now this one direction
graph there is no error okay so obviously if there's no arrows and you see
this connections obviously C is related to a a and B obviously she's related to
you and to be envied so you serious tricks there was this interconnected sets of
notes so both imply really correlations
but there is no directional component so in essence the effect of EMV and BMC
has no direction okay so this is very different from what this chain is drawn
okay now I'm not going to discuss what this is in detail right but this
is sort of another type of graph that will allow us to sort of unify
those two graphs okay and somehow to do that we need to introduce the sectional
squared note but effectively explicitly spell out these local functions these local potentials but you
have either in this undirected graphs or in the directed graphs so these are functional
and that's why this is called a photograph okay so this are the random variables
and it's a constant okay and so we would be able to how to eventually
do inference in factor graphs and not way accounting for inference both directed and undirected
model again you don't need to know anything any of this because we will spent
many lectures discussing each of this but I thought you should see this on lecture
one so now is representative of variables edges dependencies and really what we're interested is
in the lack of the edges
so the path but there is no edge between a and B that's very important
if you try to connect a to B to D to Eve than don't expect
to gain anything by doing graph theoretic approach okay so in if you have many
nodes so this is the trek high-dimensional this village h 100 the first objective when
you work with graphs is to come up with the joint probability distribution and in
particularly with the factorized form of
the joint probability distribution okay the fact is form that somehow can easily be visualized
in a graph accounting for whatever independence relations exist between these values now you can
appreciate that if the variables dependent there is no independence relations right and each of
these variables can take K values and let's say each of these columns is also
discrete and can take K values how many
values how much information you need to describe this probability distribution so you need K
values for each of them and you have via block how many variables Divinity's try
to describe this joint distribution with no independence relations at all
take away the power
the power B right so it least 10 forget about you won't be able to
do anything okay so we will see on what we can benefit take and run
up to this condition in the ventilation and drop now once somehow you can come
up with the proper authorization of this then you can stop talking about the inference
so for example if you let's say measure
the value of variable X 1 you have you know what the value is then
you can stay with the value of x 2 given X 1 where the rest
of the variables maybe you want
analyze them ok to get rid of them so obviously you appreciate that the sum
and product rule will come candy to
actually manipulate this but also Bayes  rule would be essential when you have  evidence to be able to do inference
applications really you know you just mentioned any anything right so in diaphragmatic this standard
methods in in medical diagnosis actually
almost every you know diagnosis now actually every time I am reading articles but visual
to make the systems for diagnosing diseases would take from images etc they operate with
much less chance for false alarms than the best doctor in the world right they're
extremely accurate so now it's not like
this is for mathematicians or computer scientists people in practice are actually using probably splatter
model for prognosis all the loss of diseases computer vision speech recognition Google Translate I
mean I use it you know when I go to China I always say something
and it translates and I always see what it translates to be sure it was
laced correctly because sometimes I say something and I read this like wow I'm gonna
get in trouble and so it really works very well okay I mean I have
seen it even working when there are several people speaking simultaneously with action and it
does miracles so it's really a director filtration of republished graphical models practically every topic
of the algorithm machine learning can be posed on probabilistic graphical models for okay so
we may I don't know if we have
time I covered it with ideas of blatant holy Moses model reduction in the fall
so misspent electrocuted go back and
address the ocean generalize them using graphical model so if you don't know anything about
what solvent is fine because when we post them in graphic we will post them
as new problems and so you will see sort of a modern aspect of this
algorithm and and I think you know
you like of more than a questions that without the means to visualizer the you
know error control codes and the way you
know your computer you know restart and figure out what goes wrong right and and
became properly it's really based in in
probabilistic graphical models if you take for most in engineering to take sort of you
know we talked about little to
undividable scanner there but actually the source of this adapter ones can be extremely effective
for this knowledge they're not simply random variables but the interconnected complicated systems of differing
ology and mechanical model the thermal model etc and each of them has its own
random by the Wilson within right but you have interconnected systems that speak to each
other and this is really sort of an important area for development because it points
a lot of tolerances because a lot of these systems are governed by models that
are very compassionate very expensive so so a lot of the methodologies for doing inference
would not be able to sort of
what directly you would have to do something there to simplify the representation of these
systems okay so let's you know go fast through the patient knowledge of the variables
exist already said for publicity Lester the lock opens it basically will provide information on
independence relations so graft has a number of nodes as a number of edges the
number of nodes from want to be the number of edges if we have a
directed graph basically would be this
pair s comma T where the else goes from the you know the arrow goes
convexity okay now to really you know extend this the bottom directed and directed graphs
you have to use what's called an
adjacency matrix so if you define the  adjacency matrix
GF S&amp;P little notes equals one if the ads s comma T is in this
set all right and this allows you to extend this to undirected graphs because if
you have G of s comma T equal 12 and simultaneous in G of T
comma X equal to 1 right then
this is an undirected graph there is no going from s to T and T
2 s is the same okay so two examples and I threw a lot so
far terminology here that's going to
come in the following slides but it helps to see them several times so you
have note one two three four five I am
going to call note one the road all right can you give me without rocks
or even reading the pull up slides just look on the graph what do you
think the route will be I mean wouldn't be a good this mixture I mean
you notice okay there is from you
know so so in other ways why you know the route is of five and
it's one what will be a good definition
right so so so I am repeating the answer here in this case one has
not lost coming to it okay and as we will see this implies following in
definitions when I come up with one has no father okay and with a definition
five them that is the nature of the graph five has no children okay so
five has not simply sent one is
the ornament of - all right and three you know here you know 40s -
power is two and three okay etc and to achieve what else to come together
is important and it phase again this is coming up later but I want you
to see hundreds of times so we can
communicate it says this directed a means it has no cycles of a cyclic graph
all right you noticed has no better it has no cycles someone would say this
is a cycle but actually because this is the electric graph you notice when I
go the direction of the arrows here I cannot go from four to three so
there are no cycles them okay
alright so we discussed this and then it says the notes are number in topological
order so what does not mean looks very
sensual for the left graph what do we mean - political order just looking at
this graph basically what will be sort
of your imagination share with us so the  numbering change in topological order so
I mean complain I have always one two three four five
all right the tradition hearing bit right which since we define the route to be
the note that has no parents all
right so basically we have to start numbering from the root to the leaves basically
okay and that's a topological order not to more complicated God you know this may
not be a unique topological order all right but you start majestically you are not
going to assign to the chain to the children notice that they're in the order
of numbering on the part right number the parents and the children that's the idea
here okay so 2 &amp; 3 are the children so 1 will be there to
enter it will be there similarly these are the parents of course draw the numbering
of topological order makes sense ok the same graph now if it was an undirected
graph okay these I'm pouring and lots of things because you know I want you
to see those things hundreds of times and I'm details that are going to be
discussed with lots of simple examples in coop lectures right but I want you to
see these things now so in some sense I'm claiming that the gallop you see
here it is very much the
same as that job but they see there is something going on that's a little
bit different what's the difference between the two block when you look at them okay
there are no arrows but there is
something else that is different so what is definitely when you visually look at this
two and three are connected and that's an essential step when you go from directly
drafts from directed so what are the two and three note what is common between
two and three their parent just know the
their points of what of power so when you went from a directed graph to
UM directive what you need to do is you need to be sure the parents
are married because this is not today we don't allow Mary power okay so we
marry them all right and this process methodical is called a modernization process okay people
who think that I'm you know my
let you guess religious connotations but that's the terminology moralization okay so you basically have
to marry the parents okay and actually immediately you can see when you marry the
parents you get moved in this graph okay so suddenly you went from no loops
to two loops right and and obvious
implications in the way we're going to treat this process now in the graphs once
you moralize you marry the parts
two and three we define what this whole page and if particularly of interest here
is what is called maximal cliques
okay so click is a set of interconnected no okay so for example if you
this is one two or three is a clique right because one is connected to
one squared - 3 + 2 is correct - 3 all the nodes are connected
now you say is 1 2 3 and
privately why not one employee without connected right 2 + 5 3 &amp; 5 are
not correct ok so 1 2 &amp; 3 2
3 &amp; 4 &amp; 3 &amp; 5 of what they call we called maxima please
and I can tell you and this will come in
four five lectures I don't know the idea of identifying this parchment which will be
but when we take a joint probability
distribution of this paragraph around the variables we're going to be able to write the
joint distribution as the product of potentials is with this potential behind on our table
please so the local potentials what its potential would be on automatically and that would
be actually an amazing theorem which we are going to prove right but somehow if
you have a graph like that and a probability distribution defined on this graph then
that you can decompose it on potentials defined over this box conflicts okay again think
of this as start from the
air ideas because we will discuss those as we go in underneath a course okay
so let's see the parents of a node all right you remember the conduit defining
what was the name of G this is the
adjacency matrix so the parent of a node s are all the node equal G
of T comma s is equal to R so for example the parent of non-stick
are two and five okay and
you can denote this as five six equal to point 5 or X 5 6
you know different notations I think this is participating  both notations are the ones used by
the Michael Jordan stuff the two dates of no vest are basically the notes leaf
touch of Geo Testament equal to one the
climbing of an old alright is best and the pairing suppressed and so I actually
what I was looking is like you know why
they don't like the children all right but somehow that's why maybe I never use
the terminology commonly but until we
find that this is not right in definition this is what it is there so
the family is asked and the parts of us
we already discussed route least the knows no parents to leave the know dot children
the ancestors of an LP are all
the notes s where there is a path from s to T and equal to
directed graph this path has to be a directed path if some directed basically any
path from s to T will do it and the descendants of an arrest are
all the nodes right but you
can find the trail from s to T and again in the ref graphs this
trail we have to follow the arrow so these are the ancestors and goes to
the central the [Applause] neighborhoods and it doesn't matter what I will graph we have
the immediately corrected note so the neighbors of s all the taste provided 0% equal
to one of G of T of s equal to one okay so in defining
the neighbors given even if it's a directed graph the orientation it's not important so
the degree of a node is the number of neighbors and in particular you would
see this and lots of Muslim leavening books the in-and-out degrees basically count the number
of parents and the number of children so when they say the in degrees the
number of parents they are degrees the number of children and this is sort of
an important concept because when we write the joint probability distribution we would see the
factorization will still basically with this in degrees with a number of parents retaining I
may actually show you in the slide shortly we already discuss the concept of a
directed cycle alright so in this
diagram here there is no directed cycle but you notice from this this one okay
on this there is no directed cycle all
right so a directed Pacific Loft is a directed graph with non directed cycles okay
and most of the graphs we are going to
use will be direct the strictly graphs but you know when we generalized we will
be able to go away without okay this
principle the three and the direct entry is very essential because algorithms on three are
they just implement all right and you know we wish that every graph was a
three because if it's a three we
can do inference in second so this total would be an ideal situation so an
undirected three is an undirected graph
with no cycles all right and for an undirected tree there is a single path
between any pair of nodes okay
and I'm starting with this right because I would be to be able to define
this concept of 23 for directed graphs and with an internal directory strain on directory
is an undirected graph with no
cycles okay so for example did we have an undirected three stomach work without cycles
here so this is not good then we
have reading picture anyway specimen and don't see it and maybe we'll want to come
alright for our way so you know
directory has no cycles so there is a single path from any pair of nodes
now a directed three is a directed three is a directed a strictly graph in
which every node has at most one Parliament can we tell me why do we
want one parent and how is that going to be connected with the modernization process
that I mentioned for it says the director 3 is a dog in which every
notice at most one part you
never are certified for there this equivalency of a directive three-wheeler on directly after we
did some operations which we called moralization success a directory is a dog in which
every notice of Western palate so why the authorities think has one polished because it
has two polished then what is going to happen when we transform it to know
directly graph we will marry those
parents and as a result we will get the site right so in directed three
needs to care everyone has at most one part okay now so this will be
ideal situations right to have enough directly or the direction three now if we have
directed a strictly graphical just one on one parent right and we mobilize it effectively
we will get you know we get
cycles but if the undirected glass that we get is a tree all right then
we can call this the recognizer for the pony  tree okay so let's see some examples  here
can you tell me which one this graphs is a train which to one is
a poly-tree or you know what is this car is this Satori they're coming to
our definition right over there ft3 is very very noxious of most one pilot does
this loop to be like a tree right so this actually transform in eastern undirected
graph right there will be no novelization of step so the interconnect is not in
that because you know this just this is the part that has happened father so
you have every not just one part so
there would be a single platform everybody know to any other node so this 2
3 now why is this a 33 it looks like
in a simple tree but actually it's a 43 the reason is what this night
has how many product is 2 so when you merge them all right and you
make this an undirected graph yes there is a single path from every node to
any other node but there is a
cycle there ok now obviously you know the algorithms will get a bit more complicated
when you have a poly-tree but actually when you transform this to the third form
of graph that I call it
the pasta graph but you will see that you can treat the 23 basically a
penny tree will become actually there at 3 okay and then you can apply the
standard algorithm so we've seen this cost okay but you need to change the grade
the the graph is the quad so now think this would be a fantastic for
graphs look like that this will also be fantastic so it is more complicated but
somehow we will be able to do you know develop algorithms that they have the
same complex this it will work okay so this is basically the same thing we
just discussed and the same thing
here so we talked about cliques and maximal cliques so there is this constant of
a clique is only defined for
undirected graphs and again a much more clique is the the highest number of interconnected
nodes and highest number means you cannot go and consider adding another no to the
clique without violating the property okay so this would be an essential development sir charies
a directed graph when you mobilize this to make it an undirected graph that looks
like up okay so what what parents if I married here 2 &amp; 3 right
5 this pillow and that C 7 has how
many parents has 3 votes right how's the post will have three parts well there's
some religion is allowed okay so we
marry for a 5 pollen sticks okay so alright and again you know I'm trying
this just to treat from now but yeah
we're going to discuss this in details right so you know just remember what this
process of organization means and somehow we haven't proved the district we will into this
and whatever you know how many I said well equivalent means right so we will
see when we discussed about optimization of the joint probability distribution - gross alright so
highways the goal right so let me give you without any prints or anything like
that okay because we will come back to this I would join probably distribution of
this seven variables is they compose based on the graph that you see okay so
the notation next one to seven means this is the joint probability electronic Stewart seven
and now if we have a graph right
and somebody gives you the the you know P effects want to at seven the
theory tells you what's the what is going to be the right hand side I
mean without looking at this right so
you don't look at this what is to improve ability relates to join of variables
of the two effects one touch
seven varieties will be north x one times what the effect is even worth after
and and p53 given x1 x2 etc now if
you notice general claiming well it's actually much simpler that states P of x1 times
P of x2 given X 1 P of X 3
given X 1 P notice that in the worst case there are like three arguments
in the condition can look at the graph to look at this equation and tells
me again I'm feeling nothing like I'm spying is there and can you look at
this and somehow imagine what the God tells you  but somehow it's not first this equation  without integration
well it's so basically if service Bathurst is so every which is a copter and
in this case this parcel is a
probability is a conditional probability distribution of the the variable in that note conditioned on
its parent so here I have the probability of X 1 conditioned on the parents
of X 1 what parents each
one has no extradition apparent which is one extreme condition the parents which is one
except 12 condition the parents which is 2 X tribe on 2 &amp; 3 that's
fixed on 5 &amp; 3 &amp; at 7 on 4 5 &amp; 6 now the
reason that this looks way simpler run the what the product will repel you write
the people first time we have actually said one condition of x1 x2 x3 x4
x5 x6 the fact that you don't
have X 1 X 2 X 3 X 2 X 3 means that X 7
is independent of the variables X 1 X 2
X 3 given the variables X 4 X 5 vs. now I have no proof
anything I'm just telling what the answers would be when we do the proof okay
so somehow look at the graph
you should be able to immediately just from the graph presented the composition that you
know is the correct decomposition so here I have to do calculations by chant and
try for 10 hours and addition so that you know  immediately with that perform this and
this you know you know if we had seven variables and each variable takes K
values the with no independence relations right I'm gonna need five to the seventh to
describe the joint probability distribution on the left hand side but you noticed requiring sort
of probability tables Hotel smaller size so let's say P X 1 you need K
values be affected to give an
extra on K square I'm not a counting here for the harmonization of this probabilities
make like is e this is K 3
and this is K 4 so basically if we have independence relations that you see
in the graph we haven't really proved anything again I emphasized this is lecture wrong
to just scare you so you
can not come on closely but this it's K to the fourth versus if you
have no independence at all which would be K to the sub okay so independence
relations and independence relations in the graph G no imply from the talk but let's
say no two and three are not linked right two and seven are not linked
politics on of being one is definitely so this lot of edges between knowledge is
what leads to this factorization and that's very nice because you can read it on
the clock because each of these  distributions is a factor of the  probability of hits note from this  knowledge part
145 that's when we supposed to finish all right so I'm going to continue on
this lecture with a few more examples
and then we will take things slowly and discuss all the details on directed graphs
and we will move from there
so the website I will try to put the neck strap at the latest way
tomorrow we've had the latest by tomorrow okay and and actually I'm going to tend
to those register and when I sent a copy of at least paper Bakula chapter
from Jordans butcher you can start reading  them all right so I'll see you on  Thursday